Across Europe and Central Asia,
في أنحاء أوروبا و آسيا الوسطى
approximately one million children live in large
هنالك ما يقارب المليون طفلًا يعيشون في
residential institutions, usually known as orphanages.
و التي تعرف غالبًا بـدور الأيتام
Most people imagine orphanages as a benign environment
يتصور معظم الناس دور الأيتام على أنها بيئة سليمة
that care for children.
للعناية بالأطفال.
Others know more about the living conditions there,
أما البعض الآخر فلديه علم أكبر بالأوضاع المعيشية هناك،
but still think they're a necessary evil.
و لكنهم رغم ذلك يعتقدون بأنه شر لا بد منه.
After all, where else would we put all of those children
ففي نهاية المطاف، أين سيؤول أمر كل أولئك الأطفال
who don't have any parents?
الذين فقدوا والديهم؟
But 60 years of research has demonstrated
ستون سنة من الأبحاث أثبتت
that separating children from their families
أن فصل الأطفال عن عوائلهم
and placing them in large institutions
و وضعهم في مؤسسات كبيرة
seriously harms their health and development,
تلحق ضررًا بالغًا بصحتهم و نموهم،
and this is particularly true for young babies.
خصوصًا لدى الأطفال الرضّع.
As we know, babies are born
كما نعلم جميعًا، فالأطفال يولدون
without their full muscle development,
دون نمو تام للعضلات،
and that includes the brain.
و يشمل ذلك الدماغ.
During the first three years of life, the brain grows
خلال السنوات الثلاث الأولى من الحياة، ينمو الدماغ
to its full size, with most of that growth taking place
لحجمه الكامل، معظم هذا النمو يتم
in the first six months. The brain develops
خلال الشهور الست الأولى. ينمو الدماغ
in response to experience and to stimulation.
استجابة للتجارب و التحفيزات.
Every time a young baby learns something new --
فكل مرة يتعلم الطفل الرضيع شيئًا جديدًا --
to focus its eyes,
أن يركز الرؤية،
to mimic a movement or a facial expression,
أن يحاكي التحركات أو تعابير الوجه،
to pick something up, to form a word or to sit up --
أن يكون شيئًا جديدًا، كتشكيل كلمة أو الجلوس باعتدال --
new synaptic connections are being built in the brain.
يتم تكوين اتصالات متشابكة جديدة في الدماغ.
New parents are astonished by the rapidity of this learning.
يشده الوالدين الجدد من سرعة هذا التعلم.
They are quite rightly amazed and delighted by their children's cleverness.
يسعد و يدهش الوالدين بحق من مدى ذكاء أطفالهم.
They communicate their delight to their children,
و يشاركون أطفالهم هذه السعادة،
who respond with smiles,
الذين بدورهم يستجيبون بابتسامات،
and a desire to achieve more and to learn more.
و رغبة بتحقيق المزيد و تعلم المزيد.
This forming of the powerful attachment between child and parent
نشوء هذه الصلة القوية بين الطفل و والده
provides the building blocks for physical, social,
يوفر الحجر الأساس للنمو الجسدي، و الاجتماعي،
language, cognitive and psychomotor development.
و اللغوي، و المعرفي، و الحركي.
It is the model for all future relationships with friends,
هو النموذج لكل العلاقات المستقبلية التي تنشأ بين الأطفال و أصدقائهم،
with partners and with their own children.
و شركائهم، و أطفالهم.
It happens so naturally in most families
يحدث ذلك بشكل طبيعي في معظم العائلات
that we don't even notice it. Most of us are unaware
فيصعب علينا حتى ملاحظته. يجهل معظمنا
of its importance to human development and, by extension,
مدى أهميته لنمو الإنسان، و بالتالي،
to the development of a healthy society.
أهميته لتطور مجتمع صحي.
And it's only when it goes wrong that we start to realize
فقط عندما تنشأ الآفات، نبدأ نحن
the importance of families to children.
بإدراك أهمية العائلة و الأطفال.
In August, 1993, I had my first opportunity to witness
في شهر أغسطس، من عام 1993، كانت أول فرصة لي لأشهد
on a massive scale the impact on children
التأثير الهائل على الأطفال
of institutionalization and the absence of parenting.
من قبل وضعهم في هذه المؤسسات و غياب الأبوة و الأمومة.
Those of us who remember the newspaper reports
أولئك الذين لا يزالون يتذكرون تقارير الصحف
that came out of Romania after the 1989 revolution
التي خرجت من رومانيا بعد ثورة الـ 1989
will recall the horrors of the conditions in some of those institutions.
سيستحضرون رعب الأوضاع في بعض المؤسسات.
I was asked to help the director of a large institution to
لقد تم طلب مساعدتي لمدير أحد دور الأيتام الكبيرة
help prevent the separation of children from their families.
لمنع فصل الأطفال عن عوائلهم.
Housing 550 babies, this was Ceausescu's show orphanage,
إسكان 550 طفلًا، كان هذا دار أيتام عرض تشاوشيسكو،
and so I'd been told the conditions were much better.
أخبِرتُ مسبقًا أن الأوضاع كانت أفضل بكثير،
Having worked with lots of young children, I expected
و بحكم عملي مع الكثير من الأطفال، توقعت
the institution to be a riot of noise,
أن تكون هذه المؤسسة منبعًا للضجيج،
but it was as silent as a convent.
و لكنها كانت هادئة كهدوء دير.
It was hard to believe there were any children there at all,
كان من الصعب تصديق حقيقة وجود أي طفل هنالك على الإطلاق،
yet the director showed me into room after room,
و لكن المدير أراني المؤسسة، غرفة بعد غرفة،
each containing row upon row of cots,
كل واحدة منها كانت تحتوي على صفوف متراصة من الأسرة،
in each of which lay a child staring into space.
و في كل واحد من هذه الأسرة، كان هنالك طفل ممدد يحدق في الفضاء.
In a room of 40 newborns, not one of them was crying.
في غرفة تحوي 40 مولودًا جديدًا، لم يكن هنالك أي أحد يبكي منهم.
Yet I could see soiled nappies, and I could see
كنت أرى الحفاضات المتسخة، و كنت أستطيع
that some of the children were distressed,
رؤية نكبة بعض الأطفال،
but the only noise was a low, continuous moan.
لكن الضجيج الوحيد كان أنين متواصل و منخفض.
The head nurse told me proudly,
قالت لي رئيسة الممرضات بفخر،
"You see, our children are very well-behaved."
"أترين كم أن الأطفال لدينا مهذبون"
Over the next few days, I began to realize
بعد عدة أيام، بدأت أستوعب
that this quietness was not exceptional.
أن هذا الصمت لم يكن استثنائيًّا.
The newly admitted babies would cry for the first few hours,
الطفل الجديد قد يبكي في الساعات الأولى من دخوله،
but their demands were not met, and so eventually
و لكن مطالبه لا تحقق، ففي نهاية المطاف
they learned not to bother. Within a few days,
يتعلم الطفل أن لا يبذلوا هذا العناء. في غضون بضع أيام،
they were listless, lethargic, and staring into space
يكون فاترًا، و في سبات عميق، و يحدق في الفضاء
like all the others.
كما الباقون.
Over the years, many people and news reports
على مر السنين، كثير من الناس و التقارير الصحفية
have blamed the personnel in the institutions
ألقت اللوم على أفراد تلك المؤسسات
for the harm caused to the children, but often, one member
لإلحاق الأذى بالأطفال، لكن في غالب الأمر، واحد
of staff is caring for 10, 20, and even 40 children.
من أولئك الموظفين يعتني بـ 10، 20 أو حتى 40 طفلًا.
Hence they have no option but to implement a regimented program.
لذلك ليس لديهم الخيار إلا أن يطبقوا برامج منظمة.
The children must be woken at 7 and fed at 7:30.
يجب أن يستيقظ الأطفال في الساعة السابعة صباحًا و أن يتناولوا فطورهم في الساعة السابعة و النصف.
At 8, their nappies must be changed, so a staff member
في الساعة الثامنة، يجب تغيير حفاضاتهم، لذا يقوم موظف
may have only 30 minutes to feed 10 or 20 children.
بإطعام 10 إلى 20 طفلًا خلال 30 دقيقة فقط.
If a child soils its nappy at 8:30, he will have to wait
و إذا قام طفل بتوسيخ حفاضته في الساعة 8:30، عليه أن ينتظر
several hours before it can be changed again.
عدة ساعات حتى يتم تغيير حفاضته مرة أخرى.
The child's daily contact with another human being
تواصل الطفل اليومي مع إنسان آخر
is reduced to a few hurried minutes of feeding and changing,
مخفض إلى بضع دقائق مستعجلة من الإطعام و تغيير الحفاضات،
and otherwise their only stimulation is the ceiling,
خلاف ذلك، تحفيزهم الوحيد هو السقف،
the walls or the bars of their cots.
الحائط، أو قضبان أسرتهم.
Since my first visit to Ceausescu's institution,
منذ زيارتي الأولى لمؤسسة تشاوشيسكو،
I've seen hundreds of such places across 18 countries,
رأيت مئات المؤسسات المشابهة حول أكثر من 18 دولة،
from the Czech Republic to Sudan.
من جمهورية التشيك إلى السودان.
Across all of these diverse lands and cultures,
في جميع أنحاء هذه البقاع و الحضارات،
the institutions, and the child's journey through them,
دار الأيتام، رحلة الطفولة فيهم،
is depressingly similar.
متشابهون بشكل كئيب.
Lack of stimulation often leads to self-stimulating behaviors
غياب التحفيز غالبًا ما يؤدي إلى سلوكيات ذاتية محفزة
like hand-flapping, rocking back and forth,
كضرب الأيدي، و الاهتزاز ذهابًا و إيابًا
or aggression, and in some institutions, psychiatric drugs
أو العنف، و في بعض المؤسسات يتناول الأطفال عقاقير نفسية
are used to control the behavior of these children,
للسيطرة على هذا السلوك،
whilst in others, children are tied up to prevent them
و في البعض الآخر، يربط الأطفال لمنعهم
from harming themselves or others.
من أذية أنفسهم أو الآخرين.
These children are quickly labeled as having disabilities
يوصف هؤلاء الأطفال بالإعاقة سريعًا لدى ملاحظة هذه السلوكيات
and transferred to another institution for children with disabilities.
و ينقلون إلى مؤسسات أخرى للأطفال ذو الاحتياجات الخاصة.
Most of these children will never leave the institution again.
معظمهم لا يغادر هذه المؤسسات بعد ذلك أبدًا.
For those without disabilities, at age three,
و لأؤلئك الغير مصابين بالإعاقات، يتم تحويلهم في سن الثالثة
they're transferred to another institution, and at age seven,
لمؤسسة أخرى، و في سن السابعة،
to yet another. Segregated according to age and gender,
إلى أخرى. و يفصلون تبعًا للسن و الجنس،
they are arbitrarily separated from their siblings,
و يفصلون تعسفيًّا عن إخوتهم،
often without even a chance to say goodbye.
دون اعطائهم فرصة لتوديع بعضهم البعض في معظم الأحيان.
There's rarely enough to eat. They are often hungry.
نادرًا ما يوجد غذاء كافٍ، و غالبًا ما يكونون جائعين.
The older children bully the little ones. They learn to
الأطفال الأكبر سنًّا يتنمرون على الأصغر منهم. يتعلمون
survive. They learn to defend themselves, or they go under.
البقاء. و يتعلمون الدفاع عن أنفسهم، و إلا فستكون نهايتهم.
When they leave the institution, they find it really difficult
عندما يتركون المؤسسة، يجدون صعوبة بالغة
to cope and to integrate into society.
في التعامل و الاندماج في المجتمع.
In Moldova, young women raised in institutions
في مولدوفا، الشابات اللاتي ربين في دور الأيتام
are 10 times more likely to be trafficked than their peers,
يكن أكثر عرضة للاتجار بعشر مرت عن قرانئهم،
and a Russian study found that two years after leaving institutions,
و هنالك دراسة روسية أثبتت أنه بعد مغادرة المؤسسة بسننين،
young adults, 20 percent of them had a criminal record,
20 بالمئة من الشباب كان لهم سوابق إجرامية،
14 percent were involved in prostitution,
و شارك 14 بالمئة منهم بالدعارة،
and 10 percent had taken their own lives.
و 10 بالمئة منهم أقدموا على الانتحار.
But why are there so many orphans in Europe
و لكن، لماذا يوجد الكثير من الأيتام في أوروبا
when there hasn't been a great deal of war or disaster in recent years?
مع ندرة وجود الحروب أو الكوارث في السنوات الأخيرة؟
In fact, more than 95 percent of these children have living parents,
في الواقع، أكثر من 95 في المئة من هؤلاء الأطفال لديهم أهل أحياء و يرزقون،
and societies tend to blame these parents
و المجتمعات تميل إلى لوم هؤلاء الوالدين
for abandoning these children, but research shows that
لترك أطفالهم، و لكن الأبحاث توصلت إلى
most parents want their children, and that the primary drivers
أن معظم الأهالي يريدون الاعتناء بأطفالهم، لكن الأسباب الأساسية
behind institutionalization
وراء وضعهم في هذه الدور
are poverty, disability and ethnicity.
هي الفقر، العجز و العرق.
Many countries have not developed inclusive schools,
العديد من الدول لم تطور مدارسًا شاملة،
and so even children with a very mild disability
لذا حتى الأطفال ذوي الإعاقات الطفيفة
are sent away to a residential special school,
يبعثون مباشرة إلى مدارس مختصة
at age six or seven.
في سن السادسة أو السابعة.
The institution may be hundreds of miles away from the family home.
قد تكون المؤسسة تبعد مئات الكيلومترات عن منزل العائلة.
If the family's poor, they find it difficult to visit,
و إن كانت العائلة فقيرة، تصعب عليهم زيارة أطفالهم
and gradually the relationship breaks down.
و تدريجيًّا تتهشم العلاقة بينهم.
Behind each of the million children in institutions,
وراء كل مليون طفل في هذه المؤسسات،
there is usually a story of parents who are desperate
في معظم الأحيان هنالك قصة أهل محبطون
and feel they've run out of options, like Natalia in Moldova,
و يشعرون بأنهم فقدوا كل اختيارٍ لديهم، كنتاليا في مولدوفا،
who only had enough money to feed her baby,
التي كان لديها طعام كافٍ فقط لإطعام رضيعها،
and so had to send her older son to the institution;
و لذلك توجب عليها إرسال ابنها الأكبر للمؤسسة؛
or Desi, in Bulgaria, who looked after her four children
أو ديسي، في بلغاريا، التي كانت تعتني بأطفالها الأربعة
at home until her husband died,
في المنزل إلى أن توفى زوجها،
but then she had to go out to work full time,
فتوجب عليها الخروج للعمل بدوام كامل،
and with no support, felt she had no option
و بدون أي دعم، شعرت بعدم وجود أي خيار آخر
but to place a child with disabilities in an institution;
غير أن ترسل ابنها ذو الاحتياجات الخاصة إلى مؤسسة؛
or the countless young girls too terrified to tell their parents
أو العدد اللامحدود من الفتيات اللاتي شعرن بالرهبة الشديدة من إخبار والديهن
they're pregnant, who leave their babies in a hospital;
أنهن حوامل، فيتركن صغارهن في مستشفىً؛
or the new parents, the young couple who have
أو الوالدين الجدد، الزوجين الجدد
just found out that their firstborn child has a disability,
الذين علما بإعاقة مولودهما الأول،
and instead of being provided with positive messages
و بدلًا من أن يوفر لهم رسائل إيجابية
about their child's potential, are told by the doctors,
عن إمكانية أطفالهم، يقوم الأطباء بإخبارهم،
"Forget her, leave her in the institution,
"انسوها، اتركوها في المؤسسة،
go home and make a healthy one."
اذهبوا إلى المنزل و أنجبوا واحدًا سليمًا."
This state of affairs is neither necessary nor is it inevitable.
هذه المواقف ليست ضرورية و لا حتمية.
Every child has the right to a family, deserves
كل طفل لديه الحق بأن تكون له عائلة، يستحق
and needs a family, and children are amazingly resilient.
و يحتاج عائلة، و الأطفال مرنون بشكل مثير للدهشة.
We find that if we get them out of institutions and into loving
لاحظنا أنه عندما نخرجهم مبكرًا من دور الايتام إلى
families early on, they recover their developmental delays,
عائلات محبة، يستردون هذا التأخير في النمو،
and go on to lead normal, happy lives.
و يعيشون حياة طبيعية، و سعيدة.
It's also much cheaper to provide support to families
و توفير النقود لهذه العائلات هو أيضًا أقل بكثير
than it is to provide institutions.
من توفيرها للمؤسسات.
One study suggests that a family support service
واحدة من الدراسات تبين أن خدمة دعم العائلات
costs 10 percent of an institutional placement,
أقل تكلفةً بعشرة بالمئة من إنشاء المؤسسات،
whilst good quality foster care
بينما توفير رعاية بديلة جيدة
costs usually about 30 percent.
تكلف غالبًا 30 بالمئة.
If we spend less on these children but on the right services,
إذا أنفقنا الأقل على هؤلاء الأطفال و لكن على الخدمات الصحيحة،
we can take the savings and reinvest them in high quality
نستطيع توفير الكثير و استثماره
residential care for those few children with extremely complex needs.
لتطوير رعاية سكنية ذو مواصفات عالية الجودة لأولئك الأطفال ذوي الاحتياجات المعقدة للغاية.
Across Europe, a movement is growing to shift the focus
في جميع أنحاء أوروبا، هنالك حركة آخذه بالنمو لتحويل التركيز
and transfer the resources from large institutions
و المصادر من مؤسسات الرعاية الكبيرة
that provide poor quality care to community-based services
ذات الجودة المنخفضة في تقديم الخدمات المجتمعية
that protect children from harm and allow them to develop
التي تحمي الأطفال من الأذى و تساعدهم على النمو
to their full potential. When I first started to work in Romania
لإمكانياتهم الكاملة. عندما بدأت العمل لأول مرة في رومانيا
nearly 20 years ago, there were 200,000 children living
قبل 20 سنة تقريبًا، كان هنالك 200,000 طفل يعيشون
in institutions, and more entering every day.
في دور أيتام، و الكثير يدخلونها يوميًّا.
Now, there are less than 10,000, and
أما الآن، فهم أقل بـ 10,000
family support services are provided across the country.
و خدمات دعم العائلات موفرة في جميع أنحاء الدولة.
In Moldova, despite extreme poverty and the terrible effects
في مولدوفا، بالرغم من الفقر المدقع و التأثيرات الفظيعة
of the global financial crisis, the numbers of children
إثر الأزمة المالية العالمية، أعداد الأطفال
in institutions has reduced by more than 50 percent
في المؤسسات أصبح أقل بأكثر من خمسين بالمئة.
in the last five years, and the resources are being
في السنين الخمس المنصرمة، توزع الموارد
redistributed to family support services and inclusive schools.
على خدمات دعم العائلات و المدارس الشاملة.
Many countries have developed national action plans for change.
طورت العديد من الدول خطط عمل وطنية من أجل التغيير.
The European Commission and other major donors
المفوضية الأوروبية والجهات المانحة الرئيسية الأخرى
are finding ways to divert money from institutions
تبحث عن طرق لتحويل الأموال من المؤسسات
towards family support, empowering communities
إلى دعم العائلات و تمكين المجتمعات
to look after their own children.
للعناية بأطفالهم.
But there is still much to be done to end the systematic
ولكن لا يزال هناك الكثير الذي يتعين القيام به لوضع حد لمنهجية
institutionalization of children.
وضع الأطفال في المؤسسات.
Awareness-raising is required at every level of society.
التوعية مطلوبة لكل مستوى من مستويات المجتمع.
People need to know the harm that institutions cause to children,
الناس بحاجة إلى معرفة الضرر الذي تسببه هذه المؤسسات للأطفال،
and the better alternatives that exist.
و هم بحاجة لمعرفة البدائل الأفضل المتوافرة.
If we know people who are planning to support orphanages,
إن كنا على معرفة بأناس يخططون لدعم دور الأيتام،
we should convince them to support family services instead.
قعلينا أن نقنعهم بدعم خدمات العائلات بدلًا عن ذلك.
Together, this is the one form of child abuse
معًا، هذا الشكل من أشكال الإساءة للأطفال
that we could eradicate in our lifetime.
يمكننا أن نقضي عليه في حياتنا.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)